Chapter 14.
The fifth planet was very strange.
It was the smallest of all.
There was just enough room on it for a street lamp and a lamplighter.
The little prince was not able to reach any explanation of the use of a street
lamp and a lamplighter, somewhere in the heavens, on a planet, which was so small
that it had no people, and not one house.
But he said to himself, nevertheless
he well be that this man is absurd. But he's not so absurd as the king, the
conceited man, the businessman or the tipler For at least his work has some
meaning. When he lights his street lamp, it is if he brought one more star to
life for one flower. When he puts out his lamp, he sends the flower, or the star, to
sleep.
That is a beautiful occupation.
And since it is beautiful, it is truly useful."
When he arrived on the planet he respectfully saluted the lamplighter.
"Good morning sir Why have you just put out your lamp?"
"Those are the orders," replied the lamplighter.
"Good morning."
"What are the orders?"
"The orders that I put out my lamp.
Good evening."
And he lighted his lamp again
why have you just lighted it again?"
"Those are the orders," replied the lamplighter.
"I do not understand the little prince.
"There is nothing to understand," said the lamplighter.
"Orders or orders.
Good morning."
And he put out his lamp.
Then he mopped his forehead with a handkerchief decorated with red squares
when we follow a terrible profession.
In the old days it was reasonable when I put the lamp out in the morning,
and in the evening I lighted it again all right the rest of the day for
relaxation and the rest of the night for sleep."
"And the orders have been changed since that time?"
"The orders have not been changed," said the lamplighter. "That is the tragedy!
From year to year the planet has turned more rapidly and the orders have not been changed!"
"Then what?"
asked the little prince.
"Then-- the planet now makes a complete turn every minute,
and I no longer have a single second for repose.
Once every minute I have to light my lamp and put it out!"
"That is very funny!
A day lasts only one minute, here where you live!"
"It is not funny at all set the lamplighter. "While we've been talking
together a month has gone by month?"
"Yes, a month 30 minutes 30 days.
Good evening when he lighted his lamp again.
As the little prince watched him, he felt that he loved this lamplighter
who was so faithful to his orders.
He remembered the sunsets, which he himself had gone to seek, in other days,
merely by pulling up his chair; and he wanted to help his friend.
"You know," he said, "I can tell you a way you can rest whenever you want to..."
"I always want to rest," said the lamplighter but it is possible for a man to be
faithful and lazy at the same time.
The little prince went on with his explanation: "Your planet is so small that three
strides will take you all the way around it. To be always in the sunshine, you need
only walk along rather slowly.
When you want to rest, you will walk-- and the day will last as long as you like
well That doesn't do me much good," said the lamplighter.
"The one thing I love in life is to sleep oh Then you are unlucky,"
said the little prince.
"I am unlucky," said the lamplighter.
"Good morning."
And he put out his lamp.
"That man," said the little prince to himself, as he continued father on his journey,
"that man would be scorned by all the others: by the king, by the conceited man,
by the tipler by the businessman.
Nevertheless he's the only one of them all who does not seem to me ridiculous.
Perhaps that is because he is thinking of something else besides himself."
He breathed the sigh of regret, and said to himself, again
man is the only one of them all whom I could have made my friend
it is indeed too small.
There is no room on it for two people..."
What the little prince did not dare confess was that he was sorry most of all to
leave this planet, because it was blessed every day with 1 4040 sunsets